<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief examination and censure of several medicines of late years extol'd for universal remedies, and arcana's of the highest preparation ... namely, Lockyers pill, Hughes pouder, Constantines spirit of salt, with several other of that kind, by which the art of pyrotechny is in danger of being brought into reproach and contempt ... / by George Starkey ...</title>
            <author>Starkey, George, 1627-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61316</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5272</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R457</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11942844</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11942844</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51294</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61316)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51294)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 42:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief examination and censure of several medicines of late years extol'd for universal remedies, and arcana's of the highest preparation ... namely, Lockyers pill, Hughes pouder, Constantines spirit of salt, with several other of that kind, by which the art of pyrotechny is in danger of being brought into reproach and contempt ... / by George Starkey ...</title>
                  <author>Starkey, George, 1627-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Formulae, receipts, prescriptions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51294:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51294:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEF Examination and Cenſure OF Several Medicines, of late years Extol'd for Univerſal remedies, and Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na's of the higheſt preparation;</p>
            <p>BEING Indeed ſome of them trivial toyes, by miſtake cryed up for what they are not, others dangerous virulent venoms faſlely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for rare wonder-working my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries;</p>
            <p>Namely, <hi>Lockyers</hi> pill, <hi>Hughes</hi> pouder, <hi>Conſtantines</hi> Spirit of Salt, with ſeveral other of that kind, by which the Art of Pyrotechny is in danger of being brought into Reproach and Contempt.</p>
            <p>From the injury of which pretenders true Chymiſtry is vindicated, and the diſguiſe pluckt off from Counterfeit Artiſts, who are diſcovered to be a pack of ignorant Scioliſts; and vain-glorious Boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of what they know not, nor can perform.</p>
            <p>By <hi>George Starkey,</hi> who is a Philoſopher by the Fire.</p>
            <p>Licenſed <hi>September</hi> the 30. 1664.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author 1664.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:51294:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51294:2"/>
            <head>A BRIEF Examination and Cenſure OF Several Medicines of late years Extoll'd for Univerſal remedies, and Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na's of the Higheſt preparation.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the year 1651. and continuing from that time till 1655. I began publickly to uſe in my Medicinal practiſe, ſeveral ſuccedaneous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies for the Cure of Diſeaſes, (acute eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially) of which in my Natures explication, and <hi>Helmonts</hi> vindication, as alſo in my <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rotechny</hi> aſſerted and illuſtrated, I gave a faithful account, and my Medicines were grown famous without Bills or Books, both in City and Countrey; at laſt one Mr. <hi>Mathews</hi> prevailed with me ſo far, as to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part unto him my middle way for preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and correction of Vegetables, in defect of he great Diſſolvent of <hi>Helmont</hi> and <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elſus,</hi> namely by alcalizate Salts and oyls
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51294:3"/>eſſential united together by a long digeſtion, and reiterated imbibitions.</p>
            <p>This way of preparation although a true natural way, yet at the beſt and higheſt, is but a ſuccedaneous or middle proceſs to that of the great Circulate, and this by me com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, the moſt inferior of its kind, as I have elſewhere more fully declared: For firſt it was wholly Vegetable, whereas by the ſame way Mineral Sulphurs might be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, Corrected and Exalted, and joyned with the Vegetable compoſition, by which it would have been improved in vertue an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fold. But ſecondly, it was not by far the nobleſt Vegetable preparation, which that way leads unto; For, I have upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, not onely made an union of the Salt and oyl, but alſo circulated them into a true volatile Spirit, and with them extracted Aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick and Balſamick tinctures, which being truely eſſentificated, are by <hi>Paracelſus</hi> called <hi>Vina eſſata,</hi> of which in my Pyrotechny aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted I have diſcourſed fully and plainly, which <hi>Helmont</hi> ſpeaks of in his Book of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, in theſe words. <hi>He that knows how to turn the oyl of Cinnamon, Cloves,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>into the nature of a volatile Saline Spirit, hath at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a powerful Medicine, for the Aſthma Conſumption; Palſey, Apoplexy, and inveterat Vertigo, or ſwimming of the head,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51294:3"/>will perform as much as can be expected from any Vegetable remedy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, as I elſewhere have written more at large, that way of preparation is a true na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural way, and of very general uſe in the practice of Phyſick, for <hi>(fruſtra fit per plura, quod fieri poteſt per pauciora)</hi> multitudes of truculent diſeaſes very violent and acute, are by effectual abſterſives ſafely, ſpeedily and pleaſantly taken away, without danger of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe. But where the diſeaſe reſpects the Spirits chiefly, or where in acute diſeaſes the Spirits are oppreſſed, or violently inraged (the vital ſpirits I mean) there ſuch purely defecated remedies are required, that may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate themſelves into, and relieve the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing fountain of life.</p>
            <p>Otherwiſe a powerful abſterſive, (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if it have a pacative vertue mixt with it to pacifie the enraged Archeus) will perform the deſires of both Patient and Phyſitian in Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits, Colds, Coughs, Fluxes, Fevers, Pleuriſies, tormenting gripes of wind in the Stomack or Bowels, running pains in the joynts or limbs, oppreſſion of the Stomack, want of Appetite Digeſtion, Reſt, or the like. And ſo far my pill communicated to Mr. <hi>Mathews</hi> is of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral uſe, that almoſt in any diſtemper, that ordinarily afflicts the body, it may be given with credit to the Phyſitian, and Comfort to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51294:4"/>the Patient, as in my vindication of this Pill from the unlearned Alchymiſt, and all other pretenders, I have ſufficiently declared; to which I remit the Reader, as alſo to my Pyro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techny, and Natures Explication for larger, yea, full ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>My Pill then which Mr <hi>Mathews</hi> challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for many years, is a true Correction of the lethal qualities of Opium, in which is not onely an eminent pacative vertue, but expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience ſhows it to be admirably abſterſive, by both ſweat, and urine, which abſterſive quality is heightned and advanced by the Oyls and Salt, as alſo by the addition of ſome or other abſterſive ſimples as <hi>Hellebore,</hi> black or white, <hi>Aſarum, Briony</hi> &amp;c. which are alſo by the aforeſaid Corrector of Oyl and Salt totally ſtript of all their malignity, whoſe vertues being joyned together make an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Febrifuge, and a ſingular remedy for Coughs and Fluxes.</p>
            <p>Which preparation by much experience in theſe nine years (ſince I taught Mr. <hi>Mathews</hi> to make it) I have amended and advanced beyond credit, yet the unlearned Alchymiſt making uſe of the preſs, hath made his more ordinary Pill ſo famous in City and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, that the repute of the Author is ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in the larger ſtream of his Credit and Fame, Yea, although thoſe who know
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51294:4"/>me, and deal with me, find ſo great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in goodneſs between mine and his, that they would ſcarce buy of that ſort from me at any rate, yet I finde that as long as they that learned of him, and his Widow, print every day Bills and Books, and by advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the News-book give notice far and near of their preparations, if I be ſilent, I ſhall ſpend my time in obſcurity, by which means people who never read my Books, nor heard of me, will not know me to be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, ſo I ſhall loſe the credit of my Secret, nor perhaps will ever underſtand how much I have mended this preparation, and in more difficult caſes, how far exceeding remedies I do and can prepare: but thinking this to be the beſt that can be had (the unlearned Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chymiſt fooliſhly boaſting it beyond its limits of vertue) will ſit down either content with this inferior ſort, when far nobler may be had, or hearken out after ſome other things which of late are grown famous, but are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed dangerous venoms, as I ſhall by and by more at large ſet forth.</p>
            <p>At the leaſt this medicine being now fallen into many hands, will as all things do of the like nature, grow dayly worſe and worſe, which as it will be a great loſs to thoſe that are concerned in the need of it, ſo it will fall as an inevitable diſgrace upon the Art, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51294:5"/>redound to my both dammage and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit.</p>
            <p>For Mr. <hi>Mathews</hi> was by me taught my moſt common way then in uſe, which he did not follow with that Candor as he ſhould, and might, but graſping at a vaſt trade, did too ſhamefully prevaricate in the direction he had from me, as Mr. <hi>Kendall,</hi> Mr. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews,</hi> Mr. <hi>Luddington,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Marden</hi> know, by which neglect his Pills bind the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy obſtinately, and cauſe the next day gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs, great drought, faintings, dejected ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, ſuſpenſion of wind, fottiſh drowſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, &amp;c. for want of the cloſing hand of a true Artiſt, which he, haſty to get a trade, neglected at firſt, to adviſe with me concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and having wronged me in uſing my ſecret as his own, in his own name, had not the face afterwards to addreſs himſelf to me to learn to mend, ſo that although much good be done by his pill, yet far leſs then might be done thereby, if thoſe ſymptoms had been by full and compleat preparation taken away, which affright ſome from med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with them, and diſhearten others ſo as to make them weary of, and leave uſing them.</p>
            <p>Therefore I did according to the dictate of reaſon, and impulſion of neceſſity in a ſhort Tractate vindicate that preparation from all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51294:5"/>pretenders, and have pitcht upon one gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Pill or powder, which will be more effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious then that of Mr. <hi>Mathews,</hi> or any other publickly made by many degrees, and have given a ſhort Index or Catalogue of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſecrets, with deſcription of the vertue, and directions for the uſe of this and them, the time, doſe, and manner of ordering the patient in applying them, and in what caſes they are chiefly effectual.</p>
            <p>For the neceſſity of that vindication, and Catalogue, this Apology I hope will be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory to rational perſons, and for others I ſhall take little notice whether they are pleaſed or diſcontented. As for the ſhortneſs of that Tractate I ſhall ſay no more, but that it is a neceſſary direction of ſuch whom it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, what is to be had for recovering their health and where, and how to make uſe of what is directed, for which end, ſhort and plain advice is requiſite, and ſufficient. They that would have the Philoſophy and reaſon of things at large, for ſatisfying their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I commend them to my writings al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready extant, and I ſhall God willing hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſend forth what other Tractates I have promiſed, which the ſtudious in the Art of Pyrotechny expect, and have for ſome years deſired, but ſhall not be long delayed for future.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:51294:6"/>
            <p>Thus having made a fair and friendly end with the unlearned Alchymiſt and his followers, I meet a many headed Chymical Monſter, which I muſt encounter, or elſe the Art of Pyrotechny will be in danger of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, ſcorn, and reproach, which I ſhall not willingly ſuffer to be caſt upon it, at leaſt, with colour of reaſon, and appearing juſt grounds.</p>
            <p>For of late years the formerly contemned Art of Pyrotechny, begins to have many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourers, and I may without boaſting ſay, at leaſt ten for one. Since I ſent forth my Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy for <hi>Helmont,</hi> and his way of Medicine, which was ſeconded by my Pyrotechny aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, &amp;c. and now a man would bleſs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to think what a number of Coleburners there are, and how they dayly multiply, many of whom one could ſcarce imagine of any other extraction, but that they grew out of ſome dunghil: ſuch heteroclyte pieces of Mortality, as Weavers, Taylors, Botchers, Coblers, and who not, of late have thrown aſide their bodkin and thimble, laſt, awle, and ſhuttle, and are become <hi>(Aſini ad lyram)</hi> like ſo many Apes in a Carpenters work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>room, Philoſophers of the date of <hi>Jonas</hi> Gourd, which ſprung up in a night, flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for a day, was ſmitten the next night, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51294:6"/>the ſecond day withered, and became ſcarce fit for the fire.</p>
            <p>A man might perſwade himſelf that the world were lately drowned in ignorance, as the Poets fable it was once with waters, in <hi>Deucalions</hi> time, after which <hi>Cataclyſm</hi> he and his wife <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> were taught to throw ſtones over their backs, which ſoon after became men and women, and ſo repeopled the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, in imitation of whom ſome Chymiſt or other ſurely hath lately caſt loggs of wood over his back, from whence have ſprung up ſuch ſtupid, blockiſh Philoſophers, as are or may be the ſcorn &amp; deriſion of Art and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Theſe Muſhroms in Phyloſophy dream of themſelves that they are tall Cedars in Chymiſtry, and from the Dark boſom of Nothing, they ſtraightway ſoar to the pitch of Univerſality in Medicine. It is enough for them to get a Catalogue of diſeaſes, which though they can ſcarce ſpell in true Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphy, yet will promiſe to cure them cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, with an &amp;c. That if any more diſeaſes either are, or hereafter happen to be, wo be to them at all adventure, they have a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing trifle, that ſhall deſtroy them as ſoon as they appear. I long debated with my ſelf whether or no I ſhould meddle with this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of boaſting bubbles, and their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51294:7"/>baubles, or let them go unregarded, as not worth the notice taking of a true ſon of Art, and though the latter courſe more pleaſed me, and ſuited my genius, rather to ſcorn and neglect them, then do them ſo much honour and credit, as to examine and refute them; yet at laſt I reſolved not to paſs them over in ſilence, among many other, for theſe ſpecial reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt becauſe I having publickly Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated the Excellency of Chymiſtry from its real adverſaries, and profeſt enemies, and my Books being taken notice of in the world (I may ſay with modeſty) not without ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of many that are learned and judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, not in this Nation onely, but in foreign Countries and Kingdoms, it may be juſtly expected, that I who have defended this Art from the injuries of open adverſaries, ſhould not ſuffer it to be reproached by the abſurd pretences of ſeeming Friends. For if on the one hand trifles be cryed up with the Elogies of powerful Arcana's, and on the other hand dangerous Venomes boaſted to the world for true univerſal remedies, what a door will by this means be opened to Calumny, there is none ſo blind, but may eaſily perceive.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, I having promiſed to the world in my laſt publiſhed Tractate of Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rotechny, that I would expoſe to publick
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51294:7"/>ſale true Chymical medicines, with large de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of their vertues, and full directions for their uſe, and the performance of this my promiſe having been delayed, for theſe ſeveral years, in the mean time this ſpurious off-ſpring coming abroad, with glorious titles, and golden promiſes abuſing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the ſimple and unwary. What may people think, or can they imagine, but that theſe medicines are indeed ſuch as were by me commended, or that I know and approve them to be of that vertue and Excellency which the Books written of them do boaſt in their praiſe; or at leaſt that I know no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that are better? There can be in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon no other conjecture made of my ſilence, in caſe I ſhould let paſs without animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion theſe Chymical mockeries: and well it were, if that were all, for ſome of them are ſo virulently malignant, and dangerouſly ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous, that I cannot but concur in the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of noble <hi>Helmont</hi> concerning them, to wit, that <hi>Antimony</hi> ſo long as it cauſeth vomits, and <hi>Mercury</hi> while it may be revived (and that it will eaſily be ſo long as its infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſalivative Venome remaines uncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected) are not remedies fit for an honeſt man to uſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, Since it hath been known that I was Author of that Pill for which Mr. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thews</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:51294:8"/>was famous for many years, it is now the judgement of many that I am either Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of, or have a hand in, whatever Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal medicine is cryed up, and hath a name in City and Country, and conſequently whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver infamy they ſhall deſerve for future, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the ſcore of their inſufficiency, for what they are commended, or villany in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, will in the opinion of many blemiſh my reputation, unleſs I publickly diſown and proteſt againſt them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Art it ſelf will be in hazard of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and being rejected, if not of hatred and being abhorred, when people ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve partly the ridiculous effect of ſome tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial toyes, and partly the deſperate opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome other churliſh venoms, which yet both the one, and the other, are highly extolled for true univerſal ſecrets in medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, and rare efficacious myſteries in nature, by pitiful ignorant Scioliſts, who are maſters of nothing but ignorant confidence.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It would confirm the old ſcandal, that hath been from the beginning thrown upon Chymical medicines, to wit, that they are full of Danger, and quickly either Kill or Cure. Now it behoves him that would be a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion for Pyrotechny to meet with theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches betime, and nip them in the Bud.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:51294:8"/>
               <head>Fruſtra Medicina paratur Cum malaper longas invaluëre moras.</head>
               <p n="6">6. Unleſs this remedy of diſclaiming ſuch Chymical fooleries be ſeaſonably (that is, ſpeedily applyed) the abuſed people finding their expectation (once &amp; again) deluded by ſuch quacking Empericks, will in a ſhort time come to ſuſpect all Chymical prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, for ſuch as they, or others, with little or no profit, perhaps to their Coſt, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream hazard have Experienced. They will at laſt ſtartle at the very name of a Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal medicine, as at the appearance of ſome ghaſtly Ghoſt or ſpectrum. Away will one cry with your Chymiſtry, for ſuch a time I took an univerſal Pill or Powder, and eſcaped very narrowly of being ſent by it on a fools er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand out of the world: beſides ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon took it, who in few dayes, or perhaps not many hours, was ſo perfectly cured thereby of all diſeaſes, as to lie covered with a Tombe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone. Such true reports of the pernicious effects of ſome Catholick venom, will ſtick as an indelible blot of infamy, to blemiſh true and real Chymical medicines, unleſs the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe be pluckt off from ſuch counterfeit pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, under which they march with the greateſt confidence imaginable, promiſing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51294:9"/>wonders, though upon no ground, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt truth, to the diſgrace of Pyro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techny, and its true Adept ſons, except the Cheat of them be diſcovered and laid open to the world.</p>
               <p n="7">7. And laſtly, I have been almoſt weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſollicitations, both by word of mouth, and letters from ſeveral perſons here in Town, and living in divers parts of the Countrey, to know what my judgement is concerning ſuch and ſuch (highly extolled) medicines. Whom not to undeceive and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abuſe, lying in my power to do it, would in effect be the ſame as to abuſe them. <hi>Qui non prohibet malum (quod poteſt) jubet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo I come at length to anſwer the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of ſuch who have requeſted my opinion and Cenſure of the forementioned perparations, and ſhall begin with that known by the name of</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Lockyers Pill, or <hi>Pillula extracta Radiis ſolis.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Concerning which I have ſeen and read a Tractate Written, likewiſe Tables on a board expoſed commending it without either Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or meaſure. Who was firſt Godfather to the Pill, I know not, but its name at the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51294:9"/>was as abſolute an Abortive in <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar,</hi> as the Pill it ſelf was in Philoſophy, and Pyrotechny, and was called <hi>Pilluradii Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractus ſolus,</hi> the interpretation of which would puzzle a Synod of Grammarians, though ſince the Pill hath learned ſo much true Latine, as to proclaime its name <hi>Pillula radiis ſolis extracta,</hi> which was the meaning of the former barbarous denomination, as might be collected from its gaping, rather then ſpeaking.</p>
               <p>By which licking of its name till it had ſome tolerable ſhape, as Bears are ſaid to lick their whelps, and by other manifeſt ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes, it appears that the Book in commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of this new bawble, was midwif't into the world by ſome of the forlorn hope of the Schools of learning, in reading which with ſeriouſneſs, I was ſurprized with a double admiration. Firſt, That any man of common diſcretion, ſhould run into ſuch Extravagant ſeſquipedantick Rodomontadoes in praiſe of a preparation, which is <hi>(abſit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidia dictis)</hi> one of the pooreſt, meaneſt, and moſt vulgar, that is or can be made of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> by the fire. Secondly, That ſuch a piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful toy, and more pitiful Scribble in praiſe of it, ſhould among any that pretend to reaſon find other acceptance then deriſion, his brags concerning it appearing at firſt view ſo pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pably
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51294:10"/>groſs, as to try the faith of a <hi>Solifidian,</hi> for confirmation of which wonderful effects, to have nothing but the <hi>(ipſe dixit)</hi> of one, who in his too laviſh boaſtings would out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do a profeſt Mountebanck, and yet to find ſo much credit as to become famous, ſpeaks the levity and madneſs of the people ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to ſuch a degree and height, as to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur the cenſure of <hi>Oreſtes</hi> himſelf, when moſt diſtracted.</p>
               <p>Thoſe expreſſions which I finduſed in its commendation, <hi>viz.</hi> that it is the beſt thing which ever he met with or deſires, may in ſome ſenſe be true, and we have an Engliſh proverb fit to the purpoſe, Give a fool or a child a bawble, and he will not leave it for a noble. Gold it ſelf may be, and oft is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valued by a wiſe man, no marvel then if a butterfly or a play-toy be overprized by a Schoolboy. And a pretty play-toy I muſt confeſs this is, if that were all, nor ſhould I ever cenſure it, if it did not play with the skins and lives of mankind.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not ſay of this Pill that it is <hi>prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio inſulſa,</hi> having in it a double Salt, to wit, common and Salt-petre, but this I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently affirm of it, and the Charcoal in it will confirm my ſentence, that it is <hi>Nigro carbone notanda.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that ſhall commend this, or any other
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51294:10"/>preparation like unto this ſo highly as I find that to be, if his breaſt aſſents to the truth of what he writes with his pen, deſerves to be ſent from the School of <hi>Vulcan</hi> to pick Sallets with <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> till the dew of Heaven have cooled his overheated nod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, ſo as to underſtand himſelf, and his ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations a little better then he doth.</p>
               <p>The preparation is at beſt but a Crocus of <hi>Antimony,</hi> and ſo much more churliſh then the common made as the Apothecaries pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it by fluſhing with ana of Saltpetre, by how much the neerer it comes glaſs, or <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum</hi> of Antimony. For the Charcoal, and Sea-ſalt which are mixt in the compoſition, give it an eaſier fluxibility in the fire, which quickens and makes more active, doth no way extinguiſh, correct or diminiſh the viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Antimony. As for inſtance, Let one part of Antimony be calcined with three parts of Saltpetre, the Calx (if the work be well done) will be very white, from which the ſaltneſs being ſeparated by hot water, and the powder dried, it is then called <hi>Antimonium Diaphoreticum,</hi> which may be given from ten to 30. grains, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any vomitive effect ordinarily, but if this powder before the Salt be waſhed from it, be melted in a Crucible by a ſtrong fire, then poured forth, and dulcified with warm
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51294:11"/>water, and after dryed, it gives a powder in colour rather whiter then the forementioned <hi>Antimonium Diaphoreticum,</hi> but in its chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh vomitive quality equal either to Crocus or <hi>vitrum</hi> it ſelf. So it is proportionably in this mock-preparation diſguiſed under the name of <hi>Panacaea Aurea,</hi> or <hi>Pillula radiis ſolis extracta,</hi> which two preparations (I would have the reader take notice) are the ſame and Synonymous, and do really excel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ordinary Crocus in their venoms rigor, and this is the higheſt attainment (after infinice brags and boaſtings) of theſe bungling Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, whoſe idle rhapſodies deſerve rather a ſatyrical deriſion, then any other kind of Confutation.</p>
               <p>Let no man bleſs himſelf with hopes of the Pills excellency, by reaſon of the ſmall doſe in which it is adminiſtred, for ſince its natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, ordinary, and proper effect is forcibly to provoke vomit, the leſſer the doſe is, the greater and quicker malignity it argues in that which is adminiſtred. As for the great cures that are noiſed about, and attributed to this Pill, I doubt not but theſe reports (upon moderate enquiry) will be found to be like to the ſhearing of hogs, where the ſqueaking far exceeds the wooll. I would not be underſtood as though I deny a poſſibility of great and unexpected cures by this means
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51294:11"/>but ſay, that they are adventured on with danger and hazard, by reaſon of deficiency in the Antimonies correction. Nor a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth part ſo notable and certain cures, as may be made by Antimony totally corrected, exalted, glorified and perfected, beſided the abſolute ſafety joyned with ſoverain Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in ſuch true preparations, which in theſe uncorrected venoms is not to be expected. But laſtly, compare this with other preparations of Antimony, which were once famous, till their deſperate danger, (that is inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from the vertue of ſuch falſe operations) brought them at laſt to become deſervedly infamous, and ſee if there be any thing new in this, tranſcending them; nay, if there be any odds, it is, that this not ſo effectual and ſafe as ſome of them.</p>
               <p>For there are ſeveral proceſſes in Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, the products of which, at their firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the ſtage have been extolled to the the Heavens, yet wanting real worth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm and make good their commendations, they have in ſhort time been laid aſide, like a crackt Bagpipe, or inſtrument out of tune, though their firſt appearance in publick was uſſherd in with as large a Catalogue of Cures, as this is or can be. For (as <hi>Baſilius Valentine</hi> truely ſaith, <hi>The vertues of Antimony are ſo great, and inexplicable, that no mortal man
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51294:12"/>can ever be able to ſearch out the bottom of its ſecrets and myſteries.</hi> Even crude as it comes out of the earth it is of great vertue. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit it is nothing ſo powerful, penetrative, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterſive, and renovative in its groſs ſubſtance, nor in any preparation that doth not extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh its venom, as it is when its central pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundity is by art manifeſted, and its Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num made to appear. Of which I ſhall God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing write more fully in a peculiar tractate concerning the myſteries of Antimony. Here I ſhall onely compare this new invention, with other old ones of the like kind, to ſee if we can find any thing peculiar herein, that excels the others; and upon ſerious and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber enquiry, I find no ſuch thing. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief that the ſick may expect hence, is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then that which a man half ſtarved may receive from a loaf of Bread faſtned to the point of a ſharp ſpear, and darted at him, the loaf may refreſh his hunger-pincht ſtomack, and ſave his life, but the deadly ſpear threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens as much or more danger, then the bread promiſeth relief. The tree of life is guarded with armed and angry Cherubims, whoſe flaming ſword is to be taken away by the true Artiſt, that ſo the reſtoring fruit may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed with profit and ſafety, but truſt me this <hi>Abſaloms</hi> pillar will perfom no ſuch thing. Yet it may anſwer expectation in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51294:12"/>keeping up the name and memory. <hi>Eroſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> who burnt <hi>Diana's</hi> Temple Eterniz'd his memory, when the builders of it lie buried in oblivion. A famous Quack will be longer remembred then a skilful Doctor of ordinary practice, but the memory of one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther differs exceedingly. <hi>Thais</hi> of <hi>Corinth</hi> hath outlived the remembrance of all the noble Matrons, and honeſt women, that were coetaneous with her, and ſo <hi>Lockyers</hi> Pill may be more durable then a Grave-ſtone, but ſo as to be contemned, derided, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the byword of every Practitioner, when the remembrance of its formet credit and eſteem, will add to its preſent and future in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy. Such a name I would not envy.</p>
               <p>With what applauſe did the <hi>Antimonial cup</hi> court the world, and that of late years? of which an Antient Divine, publiſhed a book in its praiſe, boaſting of as many cures done by it, as might ſerve for a prologue on a Mountebanks ſtage at Tower-hill or Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field. Beſides, the writings of moſt profound Philoſophers, were tortured upon the Rack of that Authors Ingeny, to make them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that all the excellency which in their moſt deep and myſterious ſentences, they boaſt to be in their hidden Elixars and Mercury is true of this Chymical toy. And I dare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm on my Credit, nor do I doubt but my
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51294:13"/>experience in the Art of Pyrotechny, will be believed by thoſe that know me, ſufficient to allow me for a competent judge in this caſe, that the effects of the Antimonial Cup equal at leaſt, if they exceed not the effects of this (ſo called) Golden <hi>Panacaea,</hi> or Pills extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the Solar rayes, of which I may ſay truely, It is <hi>tituli magniloqui trufa,</hi> at the beſt an Ape clad in a jacket of tiſſue, where the gay cloathing doth onely add to the beaſts deformity. But let all ſons of Art know, that diſeaſes are not to be chaſed away with ſwelling titles, and bombaſt names.</p>
               <p>What need I mind the Reader of the fame which once the Crocus of Antimony had in the world, the infuſion whereof was by <hi>Rulandus</hi> an eminent <hi>German</hi> Doctor inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled <hi>(aqua benedicta)</hi> to which he attributes many Centuries of cures, prodigiouſly admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, yea almoſt incredible. Nor hath the <hi>vitrum</hi> of Antimony wanted both its favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and admirers, as I could name ſeveral Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors both famous and learned. So alſo <hi>Mercurius vitae,</hi> reckoned by <hi>Bilichius</hi> as the Apex of Chymical preparations, though he erroneouſly aſcribes that off-ſpring to the parent Mercury (from whom alſo it hath its name) yet it is indeed wholly the product of Antimony, as experience may
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51294:13"/>make it appear to any that is ingenious in the School of <hi>Vulcan,</hi> by ocular demonſtration, beyond denial or doubt.</p>
               <p>All theſe and many other preparations of Antimony, (too tedious here to name) had their time of being extolled almoſt for work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Miracles, yet becauſe of their malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant virulency, have at length been laid aſide as ſo many dangerous fiends, not to be conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up in Medicine, without the help, Art, and advice of a very skilful Exorciſt, or Doctor.</p>
               <p>Such a Devil in a new dreſs, is this lately invented Pill, as by an ordinary flux may be made to appear in a quarter of an hour, by which means theſe Pills will quickly and eaſily give at leaſt a third part of their weight in <hi>Regulus,</hi> to the inexcuſable diſgrace of him that prepares and commends them, who very diſingeniouſly, and without the leaſt truth (as I am informed) denyes them to be at all Antimonial, of which nevertheleſs they are the moſt contemptible preparation.</p>
               <p>As for the Sun-beams which the title page, and the very name of the Pill promiſe, or ſeem to promiſe, I am confident the Maſter of the Pill cannot tell what he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands himſelf, or would have others to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by the Periphraſis. Whether they
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51294:14"/>be extracted, prepared, and maturated by the Sun-beams, as the Grammar ſenſe carries it, or they are brought to perfection by the influence of Gold, figuratively called the Sun by Philoſophers, or at leaſt have the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nature and vertue, and do that in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crocoſm, which the Sun doth in the Macro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſm, let what will be the Reaſon of that title, if they be not made by the beams or heat of the Sun, or dryed up, and brought to a Conſiſtence thereby, it is a groundleſs inſipid denomination. It is a new name ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying juſt nothing. Men are ſaid to be judged by the names they give to their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſure I am, Philoſophers may be judged by the titles they give to their ſecrets. Here is a ſecret of whoſe name and title we may ſay, as the Angel once ſaid of his name to <hi>Manoah,</hi> It is wonderful! Wonderful to me, what affinity Charcoal, Sea-ſalt, Saltpetre, and Antimony have with the Sun-beams? what the Crucible the mixture is melted in? the fire that melts it? the water that dulcifies it? the Sugar, Gums, &amp;c. that make the powder into a Pill, any of theſe, or all put together, he that can make out to my underſtanding, how they denote the Solar rayes, either really or analogically, ſhall be my Oedipus: till then my wonder will and muſt continue.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:51294:14"/>
               <p>Howbeit as I before hinted out of <hi>Baſilius Valentine,</hi> in Antimony are moſt noble ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cana's hidden, but not to be prepared by the hand of every ignorant Scioliſt, concerning which this caution of <hi>Helmont</hi> is univerſally true, and not to be neglected, that Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, while it cauſeth vomit, and ☿ while Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livative are not medicaments fit for an honeſt man to uſe.</p>
               <p>If any ſhall object that <hi>Lockyers</hi> Pill works with ſome ſcarce perceptibly, I anſwer, ſo will the Antimonial Cup, Crocus, or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum of Antimony, in a full doſe with ſome robuſt natures; but this univerſal Pill, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poyſon, is given in ſo ſmall doſe at firſt and gradually increaſed, that ſcarce Arſenick, Orpiment, or Realgar would prove lethally dangerous, if given in the ſame quantity, which beguiling nature with an inſufficient doſe, and gradual adminiſtration, is a perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious prevarication againſt the ſure rules of the true Art of Medicine, which preſcribe, that whatever noxious is given internally, be given with great caution in reſpect of the parties ſtrength, age, and other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, yet in a ſufficient quantity to work it ſelf out, leſt by this means of impoſing on natures diſcretion, with a virulent venom gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in a too ſmall doſe, an enemy be lodged
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51294:15"/>within, ready upon occaſion to work an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable miſchief, when nature beguiled by the ſmall doſe of an abſolute poyſon ſhall be leaſt aware of it, and not able to prevent, or remedy it, for where the Archeus of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack is not ſufficiently provoked to vomit, nor the pylorus, meſaraicks, and bowels to an artificial dyſentery, or purging, (as it hath fallaciouſly got a name) there at leaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident nature involves the offenſive powder (or Pill) in a flegmatick incloſure (as a ſpider doth a fly in its web) and ſo gradually as more is taken in it covers it, till with the heat of the ſtomack and continuance, this ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine break or diſſolve, then follow continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al vomitings, and looſneſs with Syncope's, deliquia's, and other tragical ſymptoms, and perhaps the life of the Patient payes for the folly of the ignorant Artiſt; at leaſt an inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible malignant Character is imprinted upon the bowels, and viſcera, which by no Art perhaps is after to be remedied, or with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream difficulty. Hence ariſe continual pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitations of the heart, involuntary ſighings, oppreſſion of the vitals, with moſt difficult breathing, as durable as the life, to the amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and horror of beholders. And truely it was to gratifie the importunate requeſts of ſeveral, who from <hi>Briſtol, Lincolnſhire, Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordſhire, Kent, Surry, Suſſex,</hi> &amp;c. have ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51294:15"/>my opinion of theſe Pills, with reciting ſeveral apparent, undeniable, inexcuſable tragedies enſuing after, and cauſed by the taking of them, that cauſed me thus far to travel in the Anatomy of them, and diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their true nature, vertue, and danger, that a record may be for future in behalf of Pyrotechny, that the Philoſopher by the fire hath publickly proteſted againſt them, and given caution to that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>No leſs Dangerous is that Mercurial prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration not more famous about the Town and in the Countrey, for its monſtrous price, then infamous for its ſalivative quality, of which an ounce of fine gold is but the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of eight grains, and that quantity ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds a ſingle doſe but one grain. This pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is onely <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> revived with a double value ſet upon the medicine by his ſucceſſor. It is an odd and old folly of the vulgar, to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue the goodneſs and excellency of a thing according to its price, ſo that it is become a proverb, far fetcht, and dear bought is for Ladies: but if it were truely known how little this powder in vertue exceeds common and ordinary precipitate, men would hardly be perſwaded to give after the rate of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and forty pounds an ounce for it, and might have the common that wants little or
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51294:16"/>nothing of its goodneſs for leſs then a ſhilling.</p>
               <p>Yet if the detrimnet of the purſe were all the miſchief that attended this old new inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I could be content to let it paſs; and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the people to be laſht for the itch of their curioſity with a ſilver whip. But when that comes to be hazarded by it, that is ſo far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then eſtate, (even the life of man kind,) for which to redeem it from the pit, man would willingly give, not onely all that he enjoyeth, but skin for skin beſides; in ſuch a caſe I cannot let it paſs without notice and cenſure, that if men will be fooliſh, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard their lives, and health to extream dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, by adventuring on unfaithful remedies; it may be on their own ſcore, and not be imputed to the inſufficiency of the Art, which is properly the fault of ignorant, yet confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Artiſts.</p>
               <p>The preparation is onely a precipitate of ☿, and if any Gold be added in precipitation, if the precipitation be made with a Corroſive, it is at beſt a deluſion, for what diſſolves meddles not with Gold, nor will <hi>aqua regia</hi> that diſſolves gold, work on it alike, when mixed with ☿, or if they were corroded to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, or by bare digeſtion precipitated,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51294:16"/>without a corroſive, ſo long as there is no alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, nor union of their natures, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct is inconſiderable, the ☿ is not in the leaſt amended of its ſalivative venom, nor is the body of ☉ in the leaſt opened or altered, but as to all medicinal vertue is dead; as it was before precipitation; ſo that it is a clog (if any thing) to the ☿; but gold reducible as before: for trial, let this powder be put in a ſmall crucible, in a heat of fuſion for <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, or a ſmaller degree, the ☿ goes away in a white ſmoak, and if a piece of gold be held over the fume in a pair of tongs, the ☿ ſtraightway cleaves to it, and whitens it, and ſtands in a pearly dew of crude ☿, if any part abide, that may be gold or ſilver; but becauſe it is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally metalline, (as it was before) it adds nothing of medicinal vertue to the ☿. I deny not but in Corroſive diſſolutions, the Corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded metal or ☿, may and doth give a deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of efficacy to the coagulated ſalt of the diſſolving ſpirit, as it is in the Lunar Pills, of which the honorable <hi>Robert Boyl</hi> Eſquire hath written much in their commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. But where ☿ is diſſolved by a Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, the product becomes too churliſh to be given (almoſt in any doſe) without waſhing away the Corroſive ſalts by warm water, and when at the ſweeteſt (that water can bring it too) the ☿ ſtill impreſſes on thoſe atoms of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51294:17"/>ſalt which remain its odious quality of ſalivation, and tormenting the the Inteſtines and viſcera; that oft times the tragical ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration thereof, becomes a ſpectacle of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and aſtoniſhment. And though ☿ may have many, and thoſe excellent vertues, in its own nature, (as the Elogy of <hi>John Woodall</hi> a famous Chirurgeon teſtifies in its praiſe) yet till a true Philoſophical preparation thereof be made, it is attended with ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay infamous qualities, and dangerous ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes, as juſtly to brand the unadviſed uſer thereof, with a mark of ignorance at beſt, if not of unfaithfulneſs and diſhoneſty.</p>
               <p>The ground of miſtake in thoſe that work both on ♁ and ☿, is the Commendation that is truely given by the ſons of Art to the Arcana's that by the labour of wiſdom, are to be prepared out of both, ſuch are the Corrallatum or Precipiolum of <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> which is his Diaceltateſſon, (of which I have written in my Catalogue and Index of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines by me prepared, with directions for their uſe &amp;c.) which cures radically the Gout, and Lues, all Fevers, the Dropſey, and Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Lungs, Kidnies and Bladder, the Horizontal gold alſo, which is truely univerſal, the Sacharine Ens, or Ladanum
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51294:17"/>of ☿ the Lily of ♁, the ſtone of the fire of <hi>Baſilius Valentine,</hi> with other of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which mundify, cleanſe and reſtore na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo as to renew the hair, the skin, and teeth, and powerfully extirpate all diſeaſes radically. After which ſecrets raſh ignorant pretenders ſeeking long in vain, fall at laſt to actual impoſture, and boaſt of trivial prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in which the form of ♁ is only diſguiſed, as if they were indeed theſe noble myſteries, when as they are onely unfaithfully prepared, incorrected poyſons, ſuch (as peſts in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth) deſerve a black mark, that they may not be a real ſcandal and reproach to true ſons of Art. To pluck off whoſe diſguiſe is the end of this tractate. To undeceive al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo as many as I can who have been ſeduced by their boaſtings, and ſwelling words of vanity, to run too great a hazard of both life and health in trying their unfaithful remedies. For whoſe ſatisfactory information, let ſuch learn from me, that the vomitive quality of ♁, and the ſalivative of ☿, do betray both their natures, as the Devil is reported to be betrayed by his cloven foot, that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they may be diſguiſed, yet their form is not changed, but by an eaſie art, and in a little time, both may be returned to their priſtine form, the ☿ to running quickſilver,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51294:18"/>and the ♁ to regulus. No marvel then if the hopes of ſuch as make uſe of them be deluded to the unexcuſable diſgrace of the preparers and extollers of ſuch dangerous ſecrets, whoſe raſhneſs will, I hope, lie no longer as a ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh on true Pyrotechny, and its Adept Sons.</p>
               <p>Beſides, theſe who deal in ☿ and ♁ pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with trivial mock preparations yet extolling their products to univerſality in medicine, there is another ſort of Chymiſts, who like Whifflers in a ſhow of Pageantry, ſerve only to make the Art of Pyrotechny appear ridiculous, ſome having gotten a knack by miſtake eſteem it for what it is not, and confidently ſo report of it, and give out concerning it both by word and writing, others lighting upon ſome ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficks, which may be uſeful, and preſcribed with credit to themſelves, and the Art, in ſuch caſes for which they are peculiar, do by undue boaſting and unreaſonable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations thereof, much bring their own judgement and the credit of the Art they profeſs, into ſuſpition and queſtion. Of the firſt ſort are they who cry up a ſpirit of Salt with the higheſt Elogy due to the beſt of its kind, which is truely made and prepared,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51294:18"/>yet inſtead of it, ſell a pitiful raſcal Phlegm of Salt, which hath truely none of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues which are duly aſcribed to that which is faithfully prepared. Of the true ſpirit of Salt <hi>Helmonts</hi> teſtimony is to be underſtood, that it hath not its peer or fellow for extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing the thirſt that afflicts feveriſh per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as alſo againſt the burning ſharpneſs of urine, yea where the bladder is actually oppreſt with a ſtone, as alſo in the ſtranguries of old perſons, that it gradually diminſheth, and pleaſantly brings away nephritical gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel and ſtones; It is alſo a moſt excellent Diuretick, and ſo very helpful in Hydropick, and Scorbutick Caſes, cleanſing and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the blood by its balſamick quality. But let the Reader conſider what ſpirit of Salt performs all this. It is that which is diſtilled from Spaniſh Salt, firſt decrepited, then melted in a Crucible, after diſſolved among ſlices of Radiſh roots, then dried again, and mixt with calcined Potters clay, and diſtilled by degrees of fire at firſt, &amp; urged at laſt with the extream fire of reverberation, and ſo continued till the Spirits be wholly drawn off. This Spirit is of a pleaſant ſent, very vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, ponderous, tincted, and exquiſitely crid, yet will not corrode common quickſilver, though in ſharpneſs it equal the moſt recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51294:19"/>oyl of Vitriol, and in weight, and is ſo volatile that you can no ſooner open the glaſs, but the fumes in form of a ſmoak will ſoon fill the room. Whereas this ſpirit which lately is cryed up in City and Country, is made of white Salt, not ſo much as dryed from its moiſture, which by lying in the air it contracts. The invention of drawing it, as to the inſtrument was <hi>Glaubers,</hi> which being of earth lets out all the ſubtle ſpirits, giving onely the flegm, which a ſmall trial will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate to any that is ingenious, for let that ſpirit be rectified with a very gentle fire, and all that is inſipid thrown away (for it is worth nothing elſe) the reſidue of a whole pound will be ſo incredibly little, that a man who hath once made the experiment, would wonder at his own levity and vanity, to be deluded by ſo palpable a trifle, in a thing that concerns not his purſe onely, but his health and life alſo, for by relying on this broken ſtaffe for help, opportunity of ſeeking out elſewhere is loſt, never to be recovered again, and this damage at leaſt is got by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed help, where the thing on which the Patient relies for performance of what he expects, and the Doctor promiſeth, cannot perform what it gives hopes of. Such may well be called cruel promiſes, where the life
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:51294:19"/>is ingaged, and the effect in an ordinary way cannot, nor will anſwer expectation. Of this ſort are ſeveral Chymical preparations, as namely <hi>Elixir proprietatis,</hi> the tincture of Corals, the Magiſtery of Pearls, &amp;c. which have onely the name of <hi>Paracelſus</hi> and <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monts</hi> ſecrets, but are not the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Such is the potable gold boaſted of by ſome, in which is nothing of remark, but the cheat of it, and diſapointment of expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in him that uſeth it. Of this ſort of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table gold that teſtimony of <hi>Gideon Harvey</hi> may be very true, that it hath no admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vertue in it, but by reaſon of its Corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive ſpirits (with which it is prepared) it hath to his knowledge cauſed dyſenteries &amp;c. which is no more then <hi>Helmont</hi> ſaid before him, to wit, that in his Tyrociny he could by Corroſives make gold appear in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſes of oyl, Vitriol, and a ſpirit, yet he could never find in thoſe preparations ſuch vertues which the Adept Philoſophers aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe to the preparations of Gold extolled by them, nay rather he found better effect in the decoction of ſome ſimple then herein. But at laſt he perceived that gold without its true proper Corroſive is dead; till (I ſay) it be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically penetrated by its Corroſive, which as <hi>Paracelſus</hi> ſaith, is truely more noble then
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:51294:20"/>the gold it ſelf. Nor is it impoſſible, but Dr. <hi>Harvey</hi> may hereafter come to find another far more ſecret potable gold, then any he hath ſeen yet, which may have other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues then that which he mentions with ſuch deſerved contempt. Then he may have a far better eſt eem of <hi>Helmont</hi> then at preſent he manifeſts; when the whimſies of his natural Theology (little better then Scripture Atheiſm or Ethnick Divinity) his Graphical de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions of the ſeveral diviſions of the Chaos, his Metaphyſical Dog-Cat, with other pretty Chimera's about fire, and the Elements, ſhall by riper years be worm'd out of his brain, then he may fall into a more ſerious conſideration of his latter end, ſet forth to him by the Emblems of his Deaths<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head and flower-pot, and at laſt perhaps prove a Sober Philoſopher. Till then I leave him for anſwer, to what he hath vomited up in diſgrace of <hi>Helmont,</hi> to his further and more judicious reading of him; his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions being ſo empty and weak, as to deſerve no further anſwer, and his Book of Archeology ſo pitifully idle, as that it hath not the good luck of thoſe Tractates which have of all others the worſt fortune, to contein ſo much in it of real value, as to requite the Readers time that he ſpends in reading it.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:51294:20"/>
               <p>But to leave Dr. <hi>Harvey,</hi> and his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table gold, and come to what we further intend, namely, to diſcover the abuſes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which the Art of Pyrotechny grones, and to diſabuſe the people who have been, and are deluded by ſuch empty bubbles, in which beſides a ſwelling outſide there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but air and vanity. I ſhall in brief re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume what I have ſaid before, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this my cenſure of unfaithful Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical remedies, they are all of them miſtakes in art, impoſed on the credulous world for what they are not, of which ſome are tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culent, and lethally dangerous, where, to wit, dangerous ſubjects are wrought upon, and the true preparation not underſtood by ſuch Tyro's as too raſhly adventure upon the work, yet they extol the products to the heavens for the true ſecrets of the Adepti, when indeed they are onely falſe names of rare Arcana's put upon real venoms, where the preparation is not true, nor the product ſafe, ſuch are <hi>Lockyers</hi> Pill, <hi>Hugh's</hi> powder, <hi>Mercurius vitae,</hi> commonly now known by that name, <hi>Aurum vitae,</hi> &amp;c. with twenty ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall impoſtures of the like nature. Others are ſafe, being of ſubjects in which lies no danger, but for want of a due preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:51294:21"/>trivial and ſophiſticate. Such is <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantines</hi> Phlegme of Salt, the common ſpirit of vitriol, the common Elixir <hi>proprietatis,</hi> Tincture of Coral, Oyl of Amber, yea what ſpirit or oyl is there, that for gain ſake is not adulterated, or the preparation ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled over, where the true way of doing it is troubleſom and difficult, or perhaps not known. Every Tyro at his firſt entrance on the art of Chymiſtry, boaſts himſelf ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way for a Coloſſus in Pyrotechny, and will adventure upon the moſt hidden myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, who knows not the keyes by which natures Cabinet is unlocked. Hence it is, that while many boaſt of high Arcana's, and yet they and their ſecrets become at laſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly contemptible, others who have ſome particular remedy not uſual, with which more real good is done, then with theſe great myſteries (whoſe cruel danger makes them at laſt ſuſpected by all, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred by them, who know and have tried them) they take this opportunity of extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling this rarity of theirs for the Apex of Chymical preparations. Thus ſpirit of Hartſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn with ſome, ſpirit of Soot with others, (called by the name of <hi>ignis vitae</hi>) ſpirit of Dead mens bones with a third ſort, are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly and unadviſedly commended as
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:51294:21"/>true Panpharmaca, and ſo uſed by many, whereas they are only urinous ſpirits, and ſo abſterſive, of which that of Hartſhorn is the beſt, but nothing comparable to that ſpirit made of it, by the circulated ſalt of <hi>Helmont</hi> and <hi>Paracelſus;</hi> by which Hartſhorn is turned into a lacteous ſpirit, and will reach the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of our conſtitution, by which means ſuch notable ſpirits do ſtrengthen the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of life, &amp; are powerfully renovative and reſtoring decayed ſtrength, and the drooping vital ſpirits. Of this ſort are Crabs eys, Pearl, and the ſtones of vegetables, and animals, the ſhells alſo of Crabs, and fiſhes, yet ſo as that there are kinds and degrees of goodneſs among them, but their preparation muſt be performed by a true Key or agent, and not according to the ſlender ſkill of an illiterate Tyro, or ignorant Scioliſt. In doing which, the concrets muſt be reſolved by a ſponta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous retrograde ſolution, and the primitive lactiform liquor ſeparated totally from the diſſolvent, which is the higheſt advancement thoſe concretes can be brought to, in which are wonderful excellencies hidden, for ſuch who have an inclination to nephritick Coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agulations of gravel, and ſtranguretical muc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous viſcidities in the bladder, which inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on though old and obſtinate, ſuch Arcana's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:51294:22"/>and by a reſtoring vertue confirm the Kidnies and bladder in their pacified ſtate, to the infinite comfort of the patient and credit of the Phyſitian. Of theſe and many other true ſecrets, I ſhall God willing put forth a diſcourſe intituled, <hi>Helmont</hi> revived, as a forerunner to which it was neceſſary to ſend forth this tractate, to undeceive the world, who have long been abuſed with adulterate raſcal preparations, inſtead of true Chymical Arcana's and medicines, to the injury of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded patients, and diſgrace of the Art, which reproach I doubt not but theſe lines of mine will for the future wipe off, and remove.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:51294:22"/>
            <head>A Concluſion to the Sons of Art and all Ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Readers.</head>
            <p>THis for the honour of the Art of Pyro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techny, in vindicating its reputation from the reproach caſt on it, by Pſeudochymiſts, I thought neceſſary to ſend into the world as a forerunner of other plain, full, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful tractates, which ſhall be onely didacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and inſtructive, of which the firſt which I intend, ſhall follow this, is a diſcovery of the two Keyes of Pyrotechny, Viz the Liquor Alchaheſt, and its ſuccedaneum, the true Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Salt of Tartar, to which I ſhall add by way of appendix, the Anatomies of Amber, Antimony, Mercury, and Saturn, by way of ſhort eſſayes, not to anticipate or preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice my Pyrotechny Triumphing, which is a large Volume. Thus at preſent, Reader, I ſhall take leave of thee, and recommend
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:51294:23"/>both my own and thy ſtudie, and pains to his bleſſing who onely can make ſucceſsful what we enterprize, and diſcover, truth to the ſtudious and ſerious ſearcher after Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſecrets; and ſhall ſubſcribe myſelf thy faithful friend, Monitor, Inſtructer and Brother,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>George Starkey,</hi> known by the title of Philoſopher by the fire.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51294:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
